In this lesson we are going to be exploring two extremely important TypeScript operators,
which is key of and type of.
These tools are the foundation for conditional types and advanced type manipulation in TypeScript.
If you want to understand how TypeScript creates flexible smart types, then you must understand
these two keywords.
As our applications grow we often want types that adapt automatically when our data changes.
Want to avoid duplicated types, prevent in the valid property access and we also want
to keep types in sync with our objects.
So the key of and the type of keywords allow TypeScript to extract information from existing
values and types instead of rewriting them manually.
Let's first of all start off with type of.
You've probably seen type of in JavaScript, but in TypeScript it has type level meaning
as well.
So let's take a look at this code here of this user object.
This is a normal JavaScript object and now underneath if we do type, user type equals type
of user, then type of it's going to extract the type of the object, not the runtime
value.
Now, if we make another object, so we do const a user to and this becomes a video const
user to, and this has a type of our new user type, let's just put some properties in here
so id equals two and say name Bob as admin can be false.
This type then updates automatically and it keeps our code in sync.
So what does likely do I mean by this?
Well we have this type to find up here because we have type of user and we use the properties.
But if we don't add an additional property on here, let's say we come in here and we say
username and let's set it to Alice123, we now get an error here because it's now expecting
our second user to have this property and that's because of this type of here we have
to find user type as a type of user which is this type here and this second user is now
picking up the actual definition of the properties that's just defined in our original
type.
But what exactly is this type of an advantage over the existing way?
So let's say we have this type that we normally define, we have a type of user with these
three properties.
It might be thinking what exactly is the advantage of the type of keyword.
So let's go through a little example to maybe make it a little bit more clear.
Let's say first of all you start off and you create yourself the user object and that's
actually just remove the existing one here just so we don't get confused.
Let's say we have user and we define a property straight on it and we say ID of one and
the name is Alice.
You're quite happy doing that and then you decide later or I think it makes sense to
create a type from this user now that we have an object.
So you're going to come a bit later and you decide to create a type called user.
You say this needs a num and ID and then we have name upstream.
So far everything matches and everything's great but imagine a few weeks later you then
decide in your code you find your object and you decide to add a property called admin so
it is admin and you pop on here and you set this to true.
Now this is all very good and it's going to continue being okay and you've just added
a property to your user objects but maybe this type is now defined in a separate file
elsewhere in a project and that had to have come completely out of step.
So this object is now the latest authority for the type rather than the actual type itself.
Of course what you might think you could do is now is update the instances of this object
and set this to a user object like this and then it's going to complain because you've
known to finding this property and you have to go back later and add a property for
is admin to your type but this approach is fine and if you have the type we want the
type to be the source of truth but in some instances in some real world cases you might
actually want the object to be the source of the truth rather than the type.
So let me show you what I mean by that let's just remove this here let's define for example
a set of roles and in here we have admin we set admin, let's do user, let that to
use there and guess set this to guest.
Now this object of course could exist to run time and we might be using it in things
like logic, I want to ask yourself a question where should the truth come from?
Is it this object or is it maybe a manually written type?
The answer really is this object.
Now let me show you what happens if we try our approach we did in the previous example
with the user, let's say we come later and we decide to set up a type of roles.
This and then we say admin is string, we have user, set to string, we have a guest set
to string.
Now we have two sources of truth, if our object changes the type must be updated manually
and this means that it's weak, quite easy to make mistakes.
But type of then solves this by reversing the relationship so instead of the type being
the source of the truth and the object depending upon it, it reverses that relationship
so the object becomes a source of truth rather than the type.
So we define our roles just like we did just here, but instead we then define our type
afterwards and do type role equals type of roles.
Now what happens is that we have our type to write from our object and not the other
way around.
Let's now have a look at another example. Now let's say for example you've got a type
of user again and we have a role of string.
And now what we do is we take a user object, we sign it to our type of user and we specify
our role of admin. We have our code and when we do this, type scripts, things internally
that role is a string but really we want role to be admin.
We need to let type scripts infer first and this is where the type of keyword comes into
a, to define our user at the top, remove the type so it's just a dynamic object like
this and then instead of this we define our type, type user equals type of object user
and then internally rather than being a string, type script will see the user role as admin
instead.
So back of our original example, what's actually happening behind the scenes is type script
is deriving our type of user type from the object that we supply.
So what it's doing kind of behind the scenes is it's actually doing type user type equals
and then it's doing the actual thing like ID number, name string is admin boolean.
And this is done in this line here so you're effectively getting this but using the
type of operator.
Now with this to find, let's talk about the next keyword which is key of and this is
going to be used to extract some keys so we're going to do type user keys and say key
or user type, now this is going to produce a union type so behind the scenes, type script
effectively doing type user keys equals ID and name, whoops name and it's admin.
So the key of turns the object keys into union of string literal types.
Now if we just find some keys from that so we do let key is user keys, if we do key
equals, for example, ID, that's fine or key equals name, that's fine but if we do key
equals email, that's now not allowed because it's not part of our user type using the
key operator which is then looking at all the properties here as a set of keys.
So we can only use the keys that actually exist in this object.
So let's have a look at a further example of this, let's just remove the code here and
then to find a function called get property, we supply an object which is a type of user
type and we give a key of type user keys, then what we can do is do a simple return object
and get the property matching the key that supplied.
Now of course we can do get property, we can provide our object of user if it existed of course
and then we can supply the property we're interested in for example name and we're going
to get Alice in this case.
This prevents us having run time bugs like accessing properties that don't actually exist.
Now we can actually make this function a little bit nicer by rather than having this
way we can actually use the power of genetics to actually make this much neater.
So let's do function again, let's say function get property.
Now we're looking for type T and we also want a generic secondary type which is going to
be the key, we can do this by giving another letter say k or the d key, we then then say
extends and extends the key of the property effectively of our type T. Now we provide our
parameters, so our object is of type T and our key is of type K. K being for example
an integer or a string or a Boolean.
Now we can do return object key and we're going to get the same thing but this time we
have our fully type safe code but it's actually now specified as a generic.
So in summary we use type of to extracted type from an object and key of to extract the
valid keys on that particular type.
Now let's type script prevent in valid properties access at compile time.